Charles Baron Clarke Papers 1867-1906 Mss.B.C555
American Philosophical Society
Charles Baron Clarke papers, 1832-1906
1867-1906
Mss.B.C555
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet 15 items
Trained at Cambridge, the botanist Charles Baron Clarke (1832-1906) entered the English colonial civil service in 1865 as inspector of schools in Bengal. Over the course of the ensuing twenty-two years, he traveled extensively in Bengal, Assam, Kashmir, Nepal, and Bhutan collecting and meticulously documenting the native flora, constructing a massive herbarium that was eventually given to the Royal Botanical Gardens at Kew. He was author of several monographs and papers on the botany of the English colonies, and at different times in his career turned his pen to discussions of ethnology, education, political economy, and Indian music. For his varied efforts, he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society, the Linnaean Society, and the Geological Society.
Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
Box 1
Related Archival Materials note
Clarke, Charles Baron, The Cyperaceae of Costa Rica. Contributions from the United States National Herbarium 10, no. 6. (Washington: G.P.O. 1907). Call no.: 580.7 Sm6
Clarke, Charles Baron, Commelynaceae et cyrtandraceae Bengalenses (Calcutta: Thacker, 1874). Call no.: 581.954 C55
Separated Materials note
Lethbridge, E., The World's History (Calcutta: Thacker, Spink & Co., 1974)
Clarke, Charles Baron, A Geographical Reader and Companion to the Atlas (London: MacMillan & Co., 1876)
Clarke, Charles Baron, On Free Trade (London, MacMillan & Co., 1903)
Clarke, Charles Baron, "Stone Monuments of the Khasi Hills," Journal of the Anthropological Institute (1874). 2 copies
[Clarke, Charles Baron, "Art. VI. Bengali Music" (S.l., n.d.)]
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired 1990.
Scope and Contents note
The Charles Baron Clarke Papers represent a small, but diverse assemblage of the correspondence of one of England's prominent colonial botanists during the last half of the nineteenth century. Consisting of fifteen letters, five pamphlets, and one photograph, the collection provides little commentary on Clarke's botanical activities, per se, but does provide valuable contextual information for understanding his position in India and his social and political views.
The most insightful letters in the collection are the two written from Bengal in 1867 and 1869 and three from Assam in 1885 and 1886 in which Clarke informs his father and elder brother, Edward, of the state of the colonial administration in Bengal and on unrest in Bengal and Burma. On balance, these letters present a picture of Clarke as a politically engaged functionary of the colonial regime, inclined to a heavy handed paternalism aimed at controlling the "native" population exemplified by his insistence in 1886 that troubles with the Burmese resistance demonstrated the need for the annexation of Burma.
The letters written after Clarke's return to England are of lesser interest, but include one memorable response to criticism of his pamphlet on free trade: "Dogs, ladies, and authors can endure anything better than silent contempt. Strong abuse of a book sells it." The last six letters in the collection -- written by Clarke to his niece, Eva Ducat, in 1905-1906 -- concern Ducat's impending visits.
The Clarke Papers include five printed works: two stemming from his position as school inspector in Bengal, and one each on the stone monuments of the Khasi hills, Bengali music, and free trade. These have been transferred to the Printed Materials Department. Two of Clarke's botanical works are also located in the Printed Materials Department.
Biographical/Historical note
Born in Andover, England, the eldest son of Turner Poulter Clarke, Charles Baron Clarke (1832-1906) developed an interest in botany early in life which he pursued avidly while employed in the colonial service in India. At Trinity College, Cambridge (1852-1856), Clarke was immersed in a socially and politically progressive set that included Henry Fawcett, Leslie Stephen, and John Rigby, and he maintained these friendships and political connections throughout the remainder of his life. Never entering politics himself, he lent assistance to Fawcett during two campaigns for office in the mid-1860s, and he occasionally entered into political discussions as a pamphleteering critic of free trade.
After receiving an MA at Lincoln's Inn in 1859, Clarke was also elected Fellow and Lecturer in Mathematics at Queen's College, Cambridge, where he remained until 1865. His interest in botany grew during his years in Cambridge, and he frequently took part in arduous hiking and botanizing expeditions in England and the continent. Although critical of some aspects of British colonial policy, he was himself a staunch colonialist, and like his elder brother before him, turned his eyes eastward to further his career.
Clarke entered the civil service in Bengal in 1865, joining the staff of Presidency College in Calcutta and winning appointment as inspector of schools in eastern Bengal. As inspector, his duties took him to schools throughout Bengal, enabling him to collect plants from a startling range of localities and habitats which he meticulously documented in building an unparalleled herbarium of native species. After his transfer to Darjeeling in 1875, Clarke found time to survey the unique flora of Nepal and Bhutan, and during a furlough in 1876, he visited Kashmir, all the while expanding the depth and breadth of his collection. Not merely a collector, Clarke published regularly on his discoveries, producing two major monographs while in India, Commelynaceae et Cyrtandraceae Bengalenses (Calcutta, 1874) and Compositae Indicae Descriptae et Secus Genera Benthamii Ordinatae (Calcutta, 1876).
During his return home on furlough from 1877 to 1879, Clarke presented his herbarium to the botanical gardens at Kew. Numbering over 25,000 specimens and 5,000 species -- the truly massive fruits of colonial natural science -- Clarke's herbarium was a sufficiently important collection to merit retaining him at Kew to assist in its description and its incorporation into volumes 2, 3, and 4 of Joseph Hooker's Flora of British India. It was not until 1883 that Clarke finally returned to India to resume his duties as inspector of schools. During this second tour of duty, he was assigned to Shillong, Assam, near the "frontier" with Burma, enabling him to collect in yet another region. In 1887, Clarke returned home for good and settled at Kew to concentrate his efforts on botany. His later publications, issued mainly through the Transactions of the Linnean Society, include studies of plants from the Philippines, Africa, South America, and Asia.
Clarke gained wide recognition in British scientific circles for his work. In addition to being named superintendent of the botanical gardens in Calcutta from 1869-1871, he became a fellow of the Linnean Society in 1867 (of which he was President from 1894-1896), of the Geological Society in 1868, and of the Royal Society (1882). Never married, Clarke died at home in Kew in 1906 after overexerting himself while bicycling.
Churchill, Randolph Henry Spencer, Lord, 1849-1895; Clarke, Edward; Clarke, Turner Poulter; Ducat, Eva; Dufferin and Ava, Frederick Temple Blackwood, Marquis of, 1826-1902; Assam (India)--Description and travel; Assam (India)--Politics and government; Botany--India; Bridges--India; Burmese War, 1885; Earthquakes--India; Free trade; Great Britain--Politics and government--1837-1901; India--Description and travel; Music--India; Muslims--India; Rice--India
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - ALS to Clarke, Turner Poulter, Vicrampore, [India], 1867 June 1.; 4 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Scope and Contents note
    Believes brother Spencer has acted honorably in his new engagement. Derby's bill will have little influence.
    The Howes talk of retiring from Indian in 1868, though Capt. Howe will likely stay if he is appointed chief of the Department. Is comfortably situated, but expenses are great.
    Doubts James would stay long on a tea plantation; if the company discovered what he truly was, he would be expelled.
    Hindus do not seem to have an extraordinary capacity in mathematics; rapine and cruelty are not a property of Hindu rule, but Mohammedan, and if the English left today, the Mohammedans would soon rule again.
  - ALS to Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906, River Megra, [India], 1869 January 31.; 4 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Howe is not likely to leave soon as the current chief, Reddie, is ill. No famine is expected for Bengal: extensive rice production.
    English politics: Gladstone and the radicals; the obscure MP Fortescue.
    Changes in the staffing at Dacca.
    Miss Brennand burns to death.
    War in Bengal with the kookies.
    Disastrous earthquake at Silchar.
    "Clarke's bridge" at Silchar.
  - ALS to Clarke, Turner Poulter, Portswood House, Kew, [England], 1879 July 20.; 1 p.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Has returned from a pleasant visit to Cheltenham.
  - ALS to Clarke, Turner Poulter, Portswood House, Kew, [England], 1879 September 13.; 1 p.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Re: Fawcett: "It is clear that everything is being sacrificed to a few big commoners: little ones are never taken any care of."
  - ALS to Clarke, Turner Poulter, Shillong, Assam, 1885 March 9.; 1 p.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Agriculture in Assam is on different terms than in England: much land, but little labor.
    Assam was depopulated by the Burmese and they do not accept vaccination, so smallpox has rendered them low.
    The enwspapers criticize the Torys for exaggerating the losses in Egypt, but Clarke feels such losses cannot be exaggerated.
    Met "that very downy youth," Randolph Churchill in Calcutta:
  - ALS to Clarke, Turner Poulter, Portswood House, Kew, [England], 1886 December 7.; 2 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Cannot send Fawcett's Life - Leslie Stephen, Life of Henry Fawcett (London, 1885) -- since he has not yet received his boxes: "perhaps the most important point in that book is the new proof... I have given of Free Trade which shuts out Fair Trade, Retaliation, shilling duties, and all that sort of nonsense."
  - ALS to Clarke, Edward, Shillong, Assam, 1886 January 7.; 4 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Cannot fathom the results of the election at home; has lost touch with English politics "as the rustics appear to have."
    Little to pick between the parties, though he prefers the moderate liberals.
    Lord Dufferin is greatly popular and all the fierce radicals are with him (there are Fenians even in Assam).
    The annexation of Burma is long overdue.
  - ALS to Clarke, Edward, Brahmaputra, [India], 1886 March 8.; 8 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Has been accompanying the Chief Commissioner on is yacht, going up the river. Complete change of regiments in Assam, pouring great force into Upper Burma. 43rd Regiment (all Gurkhas) ordered to go into Upper Burma, and the 42rd (also Gurkhas) called to replace them in Kohima.
    Changes in staffing and administration.
    Row among the Nagas lays bare the weaknesses of government schemes in trying to keep from extended across the frontier lines.
    Will reach Shillong in the first week of April.
    Has heard no more about his transfer to Burma and does not intend to volunteer as he is too near the end of his service.
  - ALS to Clarke, Turner Poulter, Portswood House, Kew, [England], 1886 December 14.; 2 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Does not object to criticism of his book: "Dogs, ladies, and authors can endure anything better than silent contempt. Strong abuse of a book sells it."
    Even H. Willett has abandoned the "Grand Old Man"; the radicals are "split all to pieces for the present."
  - ALS to Ducat, Eva, Kew, [England], 1905 July 12.; 2pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Social arrangements for Eva's visit.
  - ALS to Ducat, Eva, Kew, [England], 1905 July 14.; 1 p.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Concerns about Wednesday social meeting.
  - ALS to Ducat, Eva, Kew, [England], 1905 July 17.; 2 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Looking forward to seeing Eva, but she is not required to come.Mr. Bliss' sermon.
  - ALS to Ducat, Eva, Kew, [England], 1906 January 6.; 1 p.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Aunt and he will be glad for Eva's visit. Aunt is doing better, more often there than not there.
  - ALS to Ducat, Eva, Kew, [England], 1906 January 30.; 2 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Hears of the political victories in various parts, "But the joy of the Protectionists appears to me to resemble that of a man who has won sixpence and lost a shilling."
  - ALS to Ducat, Eva, Kew, [England], 1906 April 19.; 2 pp.; Clarke, Charles Baron, 1832-1906
    Cold winds.
- Albumen photograph of Charles Baron Clarke, [India], ca. 1870.; Unidentified photographer
  Image of an English man and woman in two-wheeled horse-drawn cart with Indian servants.